Guide to the Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, undated, 1962, 1964-1996 (bulk 1971-1995) *I-338 and *I-338A
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
JSPS staff consisted of an editor/administrator who managed the everyday organization of the JSPS offices. The managing editor also edited a monthly packet of feature articles and eventually New Voices, which began publication in 1991. Other staff included a part-time secretary, two field workers and an Israel bureau editor. JSPS sponsored conferences including the National Editors Conference, New York, West Coast and Israel Editors Conferences and in partnership with the World Zionist Organization, the Do the Right Thing Journalism Conference. JSPS co-sponsored several symposiums with RESPONSE, including a conference on "Multiculturalism, Jews and the Campus" in 1991.
North American Jewish Students Network (NETWORK)
NETWORK provided the impetus for the birth of the APPEAL and was considered the most 'sellable' of the NAJSA groups. NETWORK was student-created, student-run and involved all the politically, religiously and geographically disparate elements of the Jewish student community. In May 1969, the World Union of Jewish Students, a London-based organization, gathered 150 Jewish student leaders together in Brewster, NY to discuss issues concerning Jewish youth in the U.S. and Canada. The two main issues the Brewster conference focused on were the resurgence of interest in issues of Judaism in young people after the end of the Six Day War and strategies for organizing a Jewish student movement. A result of that meeting was the formation of NETWORK as a communications link and resource center to disseminate a wide range of information to concerned Jewish young people across the broad spectrum of North American Judaism.
NETWORK formed a central communications link between diverse groups of Jewish youth while also linking U.S. and Canadian students. Advice and help in developing student programming was disseminated through a resource center, linking students and student groups to speakers, films, educational resources, program ideas and institutional contacts. NETWORK provided encouragement for student-initiated and directed projects while stimulating "Jewish activists to reach out to other unaffiliated, uninvolved Jewish students." Finally, NETWORK served as a common forum for Jewish students, a place where the gamut of Jewish student movements from counter-culture radicals to Chassidics could talk about and act on priorities of concern as well as reach out to inactive young Jews.
NETWORK published a newspaper and The Guide to Jewish Student Groups, a compendium of Jewish student groups throughout North America. NETWORK sponsored annual conventions including a yearly conference, the New York Jewish Leaders Conference, Pan American Jewish Students Conference and the Israel Task Force. NETWORK sponsored an Israel Awareness Week (held in November), created a Yom Kippur War Israel News Hotline, held forums and conferences on Jewish women, pioneered the New Jewish Media Project, which sponsored Jewish film festivals and published a catalog of Jewish film and television; sponsored the Chavurots communal Jewish housing program, and helped to create the Jewish Arts and Crafts Community, a collective of Jewish artists and formed the Jewish Student Press Service. NETWORK also initiated the APPEAL by gathering the six original constituents under one fundraising arm. 6
While NETWORK was the forerunner of NAJSA's Constituents, the relationship eventually was strained to the point of breaking. NETWORK withdrew from the APPEAL in 1978, rejoined a few years later, and withdrew again in March 1985. The first withdrawal was instigated when the American Zionist Youth Foundation (AZYF) prompted a takeover of NETWORK, thereby invalidating NAJSA's by-laws that all Constituents were to remain free from parent organizations. The second withdrawal began in Fall 1981 when NETWORK approached the Federations on their own for funding. NETWORK stated the funds were for endowments and claimed that the NAJSA failed to secure appropriate funding from the Federations. NETWORK decided afterward to abide by the APPEAL By-laws, but strain between the two organizations increased and NETWORK withdrew permanently in March 1985.
Progressive Zionist Caucus (PZC)
The Progressive Zionist Caucus joined the APPEAL shortly after NETWORK departed, becoming an official Constituent on February 12, 1987. Founded in 1982, the PZC was the only Jewish campus organization that specifically supported the efforts of the Israeli peace movement. According to NAJSA presentation reports, PZC, "Because of its alternative Zionist approach…appeals to politically sensitive students whose concerns are not always addressed by other Jewish campus groups... PZC provides these students with a Zionist framework to support Israel which examines certain policies of the Israeli government while working for social and political change." 7
PZC chapters were located on 50 North American campuses and published the La'Inyan(To The Point) annual journal and Makor, sourcebooks providing synopses on progressive Zionist ideology and offering suggestions to progressive Zionist campus activists. The Caucus sponsored diverse campus events including speakers, films, seminars, Seders, and Arab-Jewish dialogue groups. Prominent peace activists and politicians from North America and Israel regularly spoke on campuses through PZC. PZC also sponsored seminars on Aliyah ("going up" or moving to Israel) and leadership, participated in the Spitzer Forums on Public Policy, Hillel's National Leadership Conference and in General Assemblies.
Response: A Contemporary Jewish Review (RESPONSE)
RESPONSE termed itself a 'Contemporary Jewish Review' due to its publication of articles written by student thinkers as a 'vehicle for serious political and social commentary,' providing a forum for young writers, essayists, literary critics, artists, poets and short story writers. Begun in 1967 at Columbia University by undergraduate students, RESPONSE originally began as a quarterly, but due to monetary constraints, eventually published three journals per year, one of which appeared as a double issue. RESPONSE was an editorially independent student publication, using volunteer writers and editors. The Editorial Board of RESPONSE met on a monthly basis to discuss manuscripts while a part-time, paid sales manager conducted the administrative work of the journal. RESPONSE relied almost exclusively on the monies supplied to it by the NAJSA and subscribers. The journal distributed 1000 free copies to campuses, and approximately 2000 subscribers included libraries, synagogues and private subscribers worldwide.
Issues of Response covered a wide range of topics, sometimes based on a theme. Issues focused on new fiction by American Jews, intermarriage, family life, and feminist topics; the political links of homosexuals and Jews, books reviews, the Holocaust, and the relationship of anti-Semitism to anti-Zionism. Issue #58 was devoted to symposium documents from the joint JSPS/RESPONSE symposium on "Multiculturalism, Jews and the Campus."
Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry (SSSJ)
Organized in 1964 and operated by Executive Director Glenn Richter and Jason Birnbaum, the Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry was at the forefront of organizations lobbying the Soviet Union to allow Jewish 'refuseniks' to immigrate to Israel. (The term 'refusenik' was applied to those Soviet Jews who wanted to emigrate from the Soviet Union to Israel. The Soviet government continuously refused, delayed, or denied their requests, hence the term.) SSSJ's purpose was "to aid Russian Jews by publicizing their plight, helping them learn of their Jewish heritage, aiding their efforts to emigrate, and keeping the Jews of North America informed and conscious of the ever-changing condition of the Soviet Jewish situation." SSSJ served a dual purpose: educating the public on the plight of Soviet Jews and calling to action those people, in particular the Jewish Diaspora in North America but other religious and political affiliations as well, to lobby world governments and persuade the Soviet Union to alter its policy towards its Jews. On the whole, SSSJ was a prime mover and shaker in this regard.
SSSJ utilized a system of grassroots activism and field workers to mobilize both its non-student donor base and its high school and college campus student chapters. SSSJ began a 'twinning' program, connecting American and Russian Jews in pen pal situations. 8 As part of the twinning program American students visited their Soviet counterparts, while the "Project Eyewitness" program offered American visitors the opportunity of taping interviews with the young Russians for viewing outside of the Soviet Union. SSSJ organized marathons, bike, and walkathons, mailed background materials and translations to Congress and the press, and promoted numerous innovative programs highlighting different aspects of Jewish captivity in the Soviet Union. The group also testified before Congress concerning the lack of emigration for Romanian Jews to Israel.
As the Soviet Union fell and Russia re-emerged, rules on Jewish emigration were relaxed and the focus of SSSJ moved from political action to the successful absorption of Russian Jews into Israeli society. Student volunteers assisted in language tutoring and setting up new households, among other projects. SSSJ eventually left the APPEAL as its mandate changed, leaving behind a large gap in the APPEAL constituency that the APPEAL found difficult to replace. 9
Yavneh: Religious Students Association (YAVNEH)
YAVNEH, the National Religious Students Association, was organized in 1960 'to ensure continuation of traditional Jewish life and education on campuses.' Participants in YAVNEH advocated for religious freedoms and rights, including kosher campus kitchens and test schedule coordination with Jewish holidays. YAVNEH had a staff of an executive director and secretary, and were governed by an Advisory Board and National Executive Board. With its prime focus being the religious Jewish student body, YAVNEH was the most conservative Constituent of the APPEAL. Some of its activities included an annual national convention, professional and leadership seminars, conferences, Shabbat programming, Zionist-related work, and Holocaust, Israel and Western Europe tours. Chapters were established at various campuses, each holding their own activities in addition to the nationally organized events conducted by the central office. YAVNEH also published the Kol Yavneh newspaper, but did not join the publication under the auspices of the JSPS. Tensions concerning fiscal matters arose between YAVNEH and the APPEAL, prompting YAVNEH to withdraw in January 1978. Discussions of YAVNEH rejoining the APPEAL surfaced from time to time, but never materialized.
Yugntruf: Youth for Yiddish (YUGNTRUF)
The goal of YUNGTRUF ("call to youth"), organized in 1964, was promoting the Yiddish language as a "living, vibrant part of the life of Jewish students and young adults." Transcending differences in political and religious spheres, the organization's single, committed goal was the preservation and perpetuation of Yiddish as part of the culture of the Jewish community. The New York central office coordinated activities throughout North America while YUNGTRUF members in major U.S. cities, and 25 countries, led Yiddish cultural groups. Whenever possible, fieldworkers were hired to travel around North America organizing activities such as songfests, literary discussion groups, creative writing sessions and outings. A spring annual conference was held for members and summer country study retreats (Viddish-vokhs) were conducted in the Berkshire Mountains for total Yiddish immersion. YUGNTRUF regularly participated in world Yiddish conferences and the World Council for Yiddish.
Student "graduates" of YUGNTRUF conducted accredited and informal Yiddish courses on campuses, and in 1981, a Yiddish nursery school was established. YUGNTRUF sold "Yiddish" T-shirts, buttons ("Speak Yiddish With Me"), a collection of songs written and performed by young people entitled "Vaserl," and The Yiddish Source Finder, a guide of Yiddish activities, resources and textbooks. Also published was an extensive directory of Yiddish courses throughout the world entitled Yiddish in the Classroom: An International Directory. YUNGTRUF sponsored creative workshops in Yiddish, and in 1988 published a collection of works in Yiddish entitled Vidervuks ("Regrowth"): A New Generation of Yiddish Writers.
The journal Yugntruf: A Yiddish Student Quarterly, with its fiction and non-fiction articles and edited by young adults and students, had a circulation of over 2000. Article topics varied from creative writing to works on Israel-Diaspora relations, the Holocaust, Yiddish theatre, Soviet Jewry, Jewish identity, and a section for beginning students of Yiddish. One column (Afn Ekran, "On the screen"), begun in 1987 and developing out of Spring conference discussions, focused on computers and programs written in or compatible with the Yiddish language, including software reviews, and suggested vocabulary for technological and computer science terms in Yiddish. YUNGTRUF also compiled and published "Political Terminology" lists, with words in English, Yiddish and transliterated Yiddish for words such as 'abortion', 'grass-roots', 'homeless' and 'House of Representatives.'
Footnotes
1. Triebwasser, Marc. "The Crisis in Jewish Youth Leadership."News and Views, 1972, pgs. 12-13. Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, I-338, Box 9/Folder 6, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
2. Levine, Hillel."To Share a Vision." Remarks presented at the General Luncheon Session, 38th General Assembly, Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds. Records of the Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds, I-69, Box 400/Folder 12, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
3. Ibid.
4. Zacks, Gordon."Young Leadership Looks at the Future of the Jewish Community." Luncheon Session Address, 38th Annual General Assembly, November 13, 1969. Records of the Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds, I-69, Box 400/Folder 12, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
5. Draft letter to Neil Norry, undated. Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, I-338, Box 70/Folder 10, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
6.
"What is Network: The History and Activities of the North American Jewish Students' Network," Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, I-338, Box 43/Folder 9, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
7.
Constituent allocation reports, Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, I-338, Box 35/Folders 7-12, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA, and New York, NY.
8.
Susan Dessel, NAJSA Executive Director, participated in this endeavor on behalf of the APPEAL. See Box 25, Folder 12 and Box 26, Folder 6, for correspondence between Dessel and the Partispayan and Reinberg Families. See also Box 64, Folder 3 for the UJA Women's Committee on Russian Women trip to the Soviet Union for comments from Dessel on meeting women refuseniks.
9.
Yeshiva University holds the primary Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry collection. AJHS, however, holds the Records of the New England Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry (located in Newton Centre, MA), as well as the Records of the National Conference for Soviet Jewry.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents the working proceedings of the North American Jewish Students Appeal, including the organization's work in the area of promoting Jewish identity among college youth as well as NAJSA's work on behalf of its eight primary and smaller, satellite Constituents. The collection covers the period of NAJSA's existence, from 1971 to 1996, though a few materials derive from the 1960s, mostly concerning RESPONSE, SSSJ, YAVNEH and YUNGTRUF and the founding history of NAJSA. However, the material for these four Constituents and the founding history of the NAJSA is sketchy within the collection prior to 1971. The collection can be grouped into several categories: 1) correspondence and records dealing directly with the NAJSA and its Trustees, Board, and national Jewish organizations and the interaction between the NAJSA and its Constituents; 2) financial, activity, fundraising, and promotional records of the Constituents; 3) financial and fundraising records regarding the NAJSA, including national and local Federations, constructing budgets and allocating funds to Constituents; 4) beneficiary grants awarded by the NAJSA and their impact on Jewish-related programming and publishing on the University student level; and 5) ephemera, magazines, and journals from the Constituents, beneficiaries and national Jewish organizations.
Arrangement
The series is arranged according to the original filing system of the records of the NAJSA, though in some cases, series have been artificially constructed by rearranging yearly records into more coherent categories, particularly in the case of organizational financial records, Constituent, and Beneficiary Grant files. Publications, ephemera, posters, photographs, and video and audio tape series have been created from the original series by pulling certain publications, printed matter, posters, and ephemera (buttons, t-shirts, etc.) from folders for preservation purposes and to highlight these items in conjunction with the Jewish student movement. Each series contains arrangement notes relevant to the particular series below.
The collection is organized into ten series as follows:
Series I: Board of Trustees, Governing Board, Friends and Rabbis, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 1: Board of Trustees, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 2: Governing Board, undated, 1971-1973, 1975-1995
Subseries 3: Friends, undated, 1971-1992
Subseries 4: Rabbis, undated, 1971-1991
Series II: Organizational Records, undated, 1971-1996
Subseries 1: General Records, 1970-1996
Subseries 2: Financial Records, 1971-1995
Series III: Constituent Files, undated, 1962, 1964-1995
Subseries 1: General Records, undated, 1968, 1970-1995
Subseries 2: Jewish Students Press Service (JSPS), undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 3: North American Jewish Students' Network (NETWORK), undated, 1971-1986, 1989
Subseries 4: Progressive Zionist Caucus (PZC), undated, 1986-1995
Subseries 5:Response: A Contemporary Jewish Review(Jewish Educational Services, Inc.) (RESPONSE), undated, 1970-1995
Subseries 6: Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry (with the Center for Russian Jewry) (SSSJ), undated, 1967, 1971-1991
Subseries 7: Yavneh Religious Students Organization (YAVNEH), undated, 1962, 1964, 1971-1981
Subseries 8: Yugntruf Youth for Yiddish (YUGNTRUF), undated, 1965-1966, 1971-1995
Series IV: Beneficiary Grants, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 1: General Records, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 2: Grants Made by Program Year, 1971-1995
Series V: Federations, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 1: Council of Jewish Federations (CJF), undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 2: General Assembly (GA), 1972-1994
Subseries 3: Large City Budgeting Conference (LCBC), undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 4: United Jewish Appeal (UJA), 1971-1980, 1988, 1990-1994
Subseries 5: United States Cities and Canada, undated, 1971-1995
Series VI: Fundraising, undated, 1972-[1996]
Series VII: Publications and Printed Matter, undated, 1969, 1971-1995
Subseries 1: Constituents: Journals, Newsletters, Newspapers and Printed Matter, undated, 1969, 1971, 1973, 1976-1978, 1984, 1986-1993
Subseries 2: Beneficiaries: Journals, Newsletters, Newspapers and Printed Matter, undated, 1969, 1973-1995
Subseries 3: Others: Journals, Newsletters, Newspapers and Printed Matter, undated, 1971-1995
Series VIII: Ephemera and Posters, undated, 1971-1995
Subseries 1: Ephemera, undated, 1973-1995
Subseries 2: Posters, undated, 1973-1994
Series IX: Photographs, undated, 1972-1995
Series X: Video and Audio Tapes, undated, 1990s
Collection Addendum I-338A: North American Jewish Students Appeal, undated, 1967-1995
Provenance
The Records of the North American Jewish Students Appeal were donated to the American Jewish Historical Society by Brenda Gervertz, Executive Director of the organization from 1989-1995. Additional materials from various collections were added to expand partial runs of periodicals in the original collection.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to all researchers by permission of the Executive Director of the American Jewish Historical Society, except items that are restricted due to their fragility.
Related Material
I-59, CJF Oral Histories, Charles Zibbel
I-61, Jewish Student Organizations
I-69, Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds
I-181, National Conference on Soviet Jewry
I-237, New England Struggle for Soviet Jewry(located in Newton Centre, MA)
I-248, Jewish Student Press Service
I-250, Breira
Unprocessed, Lights in Action
Library,Response Journal Collection
Container List
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series I: Board of Trustees, Governing Board, Friends and Rabbis, undated, 1971-1995; Boxes 1-15.
  Arranged in four subseries:Subseries 1: Board of Trustees,Subseries 2: Governing Board,Subseries 3: Friends,Subseries 4: Rabbis.
  Series I documents correspondence, memos, and minutes of the APPEAL, as well as the APPEAL's solicitation campaigns regarding Trustees, Friends and Rabbis. Series I documents the inner workings of the APPEAL, including advice solicited from its Trustees, the interaction of the Governing Board and Trustees and the workings of the Governing Board. The monetary and spiritual support received from the wider Jewish community towards the basic ideals of the APPEAL's social and political agenda is reflected in the subseries concerning Friends and Rabbis. The series is documented in four parts, as follows.
  - Subseries 1: Board of Trustees, undated, 1971-1995; Boxes 1-9 (Folders 1-6).
    Arranged into two informal subcategories,General Records and Trustee Correspondence and Member Lists, alphabetically.